all right Bretton Heather here perched
on a hillside near Mount Shasta to talk
in light of your recent publication in
Collett Heather and some of the feedback
that you've gotten we're gonna talk a
little bit about sex and in particular
we're gonna talk about some of the
evolutionary lens through which one
might view sex start with a basic is it
better to be a man or a woman yes yes
yes it is better to be it is it is
neither better to be male nor female in
any population that is experiencing sex
ratios the likes of which every
population that we know of with
exceedingly rare exceptions have
experienced throughout history yes but
you evaded the question I asked you man
or woman I've always enjoyed being
female you've always enjoyed it I've
always enjoyed you being male I see yes
well being straight and all and it is a
mathematical inevitability that either
sex which is limiting which there are
not enough will be produced in greater
numbers the next generation because they
will be the more valuable it sounds very
technical but in the case of many women
is it not clear that it is better to be
a man because if you play your cards
right you get to go to bed with women ah
see now that said said like a straight
man my favorite so my feeling is as you
might imagine the corollary which is
that not really even having to play your
cards right you get to engage with with
men sexually but if you play your cards
right you get to go to bed as you say
with excellent yes I see that's all very
confusing I can't imagine why anyone
would want to do it and I must say
should reincarnation be a real thing
which I assume it isn't since there is
zero evidence for it but if it's a real
thing I
hope assuming that reincarnation does
not involve us interacting in the future
I hope you do come back as as a man so
that you can test your hypothesis all
right well somehow yeah there's tracks
right over there yes so we've gotta off
the rails without even being near that
we were we did not start out on the
rails I will grant you that all right so
let's let's go back to the question that
you seemed insistence on attempting to
answer here which is is it better to be
male or female is it not obvious that it
is better to be male because in most
species males can produce huge numbers
of offspring and females because they
invest more in each offspring produce
smaller numbers so evolution being what
it is and it having something to do with
producing large numbers of offspring
isn't it evolutionarily better to be
male no because every man imagines that
he's that guy that he's gonna be the
Genghis Khan of his generation and
produce more kids than anyone else ever
has and of course no modern man is
thinking in terms of production of kids
but the proxy is I'm gonna have a lot of
sites a lot of sites of all women may be
settling down but also keeping my eye
out for all the other sexual
opportunities that are out there most
men aren't that guy and so any
population in which there is a gig is
gone there are many many men getting a
late start at it that's for sure we
could agree that as Genghis Khan's go
I'm not a you know an early bloomer well
we agree that you're gonna keep your
eyes on the prize that is our children
that are already extent the universe
yeah yeah yeah no they're my first
priority for sure okay in a population
where Genghis Khan exists there are
going to be a ton of men who are
involuntarily celibate
whereas in any population across human
history and indeed across the broad
swath of other organisms all females in
the pre producer and so the variation
the variability in what is called
reproductive success for females is far
lower from the variability in
reproductive success for males and in
fact we see that greater male
variability hypothesis born out in a
number of other areas
things like mathematical ability as well
but in terms of reproductive success the
male who has reproduced the most has had
far more kids than then any woman could
and certainly there are some women who
have had no children and some men who
have had no children so it would appear
that the lower limit is just the same
and while the number is the same zero
the number of men throughout history who
have left no offspring is an order of
magnitude higher than the percentage of
women in any given population who leave
the hospital so if we imagine that the
average man sits at some position in
terms of number of offspring that he
leaves in any given moment in history
for everyone who beats the odds there's
one who under performs is that fair to
say and so the same thing is true for
females because it takes a male and a
female to produce offspring in creatures
like us there are there is an equal
average in the population for the number
of offspring produced but the variance
is much greater for males right so so in
any population we're polygyny often more
generically and slightly less precisely
called polygamy in any population where
polygamy is norm there will be more
women than men reproducing in the
population but that does not change the
fact that every single one of us barring
the gross cases of incest have an
exactly equal number of male and female
ancestors okay so in a case let's say
it's human beings and there's been a war
that has eliminated a large number of
men from a population is it now better
to be male or female better in terms of
that like at that moment in time if you
were a parent producing offspring would
it be better to produce male offspring
or female offspring at that instant
well actually the answer is the same in
the moment you are going to produce more
kids if you're male because you are
males are limiting therefore you are a
rare commodity and into the next
generation especially if you can produce
kids quickly that is likely to be the
case
in until it corrects and so pretty boys
are for the moment going to be more
valuable and therefore produced in
greater numbers so and the inverse would
also be true in the case where for
instance there has been a lot of sex
selective abortion as is true in some
cultures women are limiting and
therefore women become more valuable and
and have greater choice among partners
when they come of age which I must say
raises a deep question that I've never
heard well answered and I'm afraid the
answer is actually quite frightening but
in a culture where women are less common
because of selective abortion you should
imagine that women would be in high
demand and therefore they should be
prized as offspring and yet that is not
typically what we understand from such
cultures so that's a mystery that we
have to address separately but norms
don't change as quickly as we think they
should be able to I actually don't think
that cuts it oh I don't know I don't
think it's full fully explanatory but
it's true I think that is an observation
without being particularly explanatory I
think there is something about the fact
that the cultural norm which obviously
could turn on a dime does not shift in
the direction of female offspring that
suggests that actually an overproduction
of male offspring has a value that we
have yet to describe well we've been
talking about about adaptive value at
the individual level and a population
will be better suited to something like
warfare if it has an over production
with men yeah but our field has yet to
acknowledge that that level of selection
exists and so in some sense I think we
are upended here by the fact that we
don't have the right tools yet but so
let's let's just finish out the general
biological case it's not better to be
male or female
because although the variance is higher
for males and therefore a super
successful male is better than a super
successful female from the perspective
of how many offspring he produces the
chances of underperforming counteract
the value of over-performing so that
males and females end up dead even and
and in a stable population which of
course humans on earth parts they're a
growing population
a stable population on average every man
and every woman produces two offspring
that survive to reproduce with the next
generation two and only two no matter
how many they produce no matter if there
are frogs that produce 10,000 for mating
event or people who produce one in a
stable population isn't it growing it is
again mathematically true that only two
of those children that were produced via
sexual means as opposed to you some kind
of basically production like like
cloning or according to josephus will
survive to reproduce themselves yep I
always try to be careful about this
because when you say every you're
talking about on average and of course
there's nothing that says you can't have
some couples that wildly overproduced
the two offspring that would read that
would replace them in the population and
other couples underperform it just the
same way individuals can over perform or
underperform but on average in a stable
population every pair produces two
offspring that survive to reproduce and
that's just simply a mathematical
mathematical fact
but the logic to walk away from this
with is from the point of view of
producing offspring males and females in
a population in which males and females
are equally common are equally valuable
there are reasons that an individual
might want to produce males or females
if that individual knows something about
what sorts of offspring it's going to
produce but absent that information
males and females are equally valuable
in a population in which either males or
females have become rare producing the
rare sex has disproportionate value and
so there are moments in time at which
the logic does not hold for a given
population and being one or the other is
better but there is not a bias in terms
of which sex ought to be better in other
words it's whatever sex happens to be in
short supply that maybe males because
males are risk takers it may be more
frequent that males are in low supply
and therefore producing males will have
a an extra benefit for the parents who
do it but in general it's a matter of
which sex has become rare historically
the risks to males have been things like
hunting and warfare and the risks to
females have been in humans childbirth
hunting warfare and anything that
follows hold my beer more watch this
yeah that that's a biggie for men
sometimes for boys look ma no hands
look ma no hands or hold my root beer
also that's one sometimes yeah all right
well I think this is a good introductory
lesson in terms of how to think about
sex from an evolutionary perspective hey
folks if you like this video click like
subscribe to the channel and if you feel
like supporting the creation of more
content like this head on over to my
patreon page and sign up at whatever
level feels comfortable